Hello. I'm Gunho Shin from DAY1COMPANY.
Today's topic is "Highly Advanced AX is Indistinguishable from Entrepreneurship."
That's the theme.
I made the slides quite text-heavy,
but since the presentation materials will be shared afterwards,
I wrote them so you can understand the details by reading them.
Let me go through this quickly.
Three things for today.
First, I'll share what I learned from losing AX opportunities,
explaining why highly advanced AX is indistinguishable from entrepreneurship,
and from that perspective, I prepared this presentation to share my AX playbook rules.
Let me start with the first point.
Since today is Echo & Delta, I'm going to claim that I'm an AX consultant,
so I brought a brief overview of my career path.
So about consultants.
A characteristic of consultants is that they always have a broad but shallow skill set,
and now I'm serving as the Head of B2B Division at DAY1COMPANY,
tasked with generating revenue or operating profit.
So I'm doing BD.
What's really scary is what I realized after doing BD for a year -
I worked logically.
And?
So I solved problems.
So did that generate revenue and profit?
I should be able to answer that, and it's quite scary.
Because if it doesn't work out, 100 people's salaries are at stake,
so 2025 was a year with enormous pressure.
Before that, I was a PO at DOIT, did consulting for over 2 years,
then did Python-based modeling in the financial sector,
then dabbled in ML/DL at Karst,
so I have a history of developing an engineer's mindset.
So at my current company, as Head of Division, my role is to bring in money.
Fortunately, I'm in an environment where I can explore the topic of AX deeply.
Since we provide AX training extensively to enterprise-level customers,
I get to hear a lot about what AX needs exist at the corporate level.
After all, wanting AX training means they want to do AX, right?
So naturally I hear these needs, but of course they're vague.
The training they want is also vague,
so now these early adopter-like
customers - I meet them, diagnose their needs, structure them, and say "this is the training you need."
Through this process, I thought we could launch a new business combining consulting and SRL,
so we're planning to launch it next year.
If external customers are on the left,
internally, my goal isn't to do AX per se - I need to make money,
and increasing productivity is the best number one priority,
and since it's currently AX, I've tried all sorts of things.
To increase productivity,
internal training alone doesn't improve productivity,
so I thought "I need to build this myself,"
built it and deployed those projects.
GPTs projects, dashboards, James GPTs that makes agents - I've been actively trying to deploy these.
This November, I aggressively set up an AI Transformation team,
but of course, as Donghun mentioned, resources aren't sufficient.
"I don't care what you do, just make money" - that's the mandate,
so I can't open job postings,
so I just picked the four smartest people from the training team and reassigned them.
They didn't know n8n, but started studying it,
and now after various trials and errors, they're completely rebuilding the proposal Workflow.
Once Ridi fixes it, it eventually outputs to customers as a PPT proposal.
It seems to be going pretty well actually.
That's my current situation with AX.
My core question is: How can we make AI Transformation successful?
And beyond individual productivity, how do we manage this at the organizational level?
I believe those attending today probably have the same questions.
Now, about the technology adoption curve -
where do you think today's attendees are on this curve?
You're probably right here, of course,
but from my experience doing AX meetings and training for large enterprises and looking at internal operations,
people here are around this point.
So you're extremely outlier-level individuals.
Where is my organization's leadership from a business perspective?
If they're here, great.
And where are the counterparties I need to transform -
marketing team, training team, sales team - if they're here, great.
But to increase organizational productivity beyond individual productivity,
I have to force this on these people.
So it's something I have to do.
I have to do all this with them, and they're usually like this.
"Why should I coordinate with you?" - it ends up being a difficult task.
And C-level executives don't easily give resources.
From that perspective, unless you're in a leadership position in this era,
the opportunity itself to do organization-level AX
is limited to maybe two or three tries even for leaders.
So what I want to say is, since it's this difficult,
if I share what I learned from successful and failed AX attempts,
maybe you can reduce trial and error?
Maybe waste fewer tickets?
The first thing I did was
to start with building a proposal search system beyond just training.
So we have training consultants who hear client needs
and design training to propose - that workflow exists.
So I proceeded by the book initially.
Obviously interviewed and mapped the workflow.
Drew it all out.
So before I made agents that could draw these,
I built it so when this goes in, that comes out.
Wow! Amazing! Great! - thinking that.
Built it, and obviously after workflow analysis, what do you do next?
Bottleneck analysis, right?
So I looked and found that collecting internal materials
was consuming too much time.
So depending on client characteristics, the proposals to reference are different,
but they're all in Drive, 300 of them, having to open and check each one.
I thought "This is a perfect low hanging fruit for AX" and built it.
Resources invested - at that time there was a strategy team,
practitioner interviews, the production team summarized, I planned,
the Product Group Head developed it, first deployment, feedback, second deployment, etc.
And then it failed.
Nobody really uses it now.
It's just sitting there abandoned.
So that was one failed AX case.
But then, among various attempts, the successful one
was the Skills Consulting service pipeline.
AX-ing this service was a very successful experience.
To explain simply, Skills Consulting is
for battery solutions, EV batteries companies,
from Rbnp, about 80 teams and 100 job roles,
defining the software skills they need and building the training system.
18 weeks, something like that.
What I want to say is, when we do Skills Consulting for places like Lotte Department Store,
this becomes Skills Consulting.
What I want to say is, this is Skills Consulting for places like Lotte Department Store.
this is Skills Consulting.
What I want to say is this is Skills Consulting.
This team handles it, but since I was a consultant,
I immediately sensed that keeping this under me would cause problems.
I felt that even with minimum 4 people pulling all-nighters for 2 weeks straight, time would be short.
At that time there was no workflow analyzer or anything,
so I built all the logic from start to finish and made agents,
and finally deployed the interview questionnaire creation via vibe coding.
Obviously in that process, to establish the logic
as an agent, as a consultant, I worked out all the questions with GPT.
I developed this myself.
Then after mapping out the AX pipeline for this difficult consulting work,
I ran about 5 iterations by myself.
Built the logic, saw it cost up to 3000 won, realized the logic was too heavy.
Came back and redid everything from start to finish.
What was really interesting is that in consulting,
you can't run these kinds of iterations. Unlike development.
You have to grind through manually and only see results 8 weeks later.
But working with AI, I ran 5 iterations and then deployed to the team.
So I alone spent 5 hours each on Saturday, Sunday, Monday to build and bring it - it's quite complex.
5 GPTs are connected, JSON from #1 goes into #2,
then the GPT analysis result from #2 goes sequentially into the next, and so on until this point.
Then when you upload, it creates the interview questionnaire in Excel.
In a way, this was a much more unfamiliar workflow
than the proposal system, and I wondered if the people who actually understand this would use it.
But this was actually a huge success. Everyone switched over.
They don't know what JSON is, but they use it. Just going to this webpage link.
Working in companies, when you tell people "go to this link and use it," they never do.
Those links get abandoned, but this one - everyone switched to the new workflow at near suicide-squad level.
So I thought the decisive difference is just one thing.
First, I learned that the magnitude of utility determines AX success.
Looking at the failure, the existing proposal search time was about 1-2 hours, about 1 hour,
and using this reduced it to about 15 minutes.
About 4x improvement.
In the AX success case, if you didn't use this and didn't switch workflows, doing it the old way
would take 120 hours working 12 hours a day for 2 weeks,
but using this you can finish today and go home.
Then everyone uses it.
So I always thought 10x, 20x efficiency means I'll definitely switch.
4x, 30x - not a chance.
Reflecting on why else it succeeded:
the pain size was large, it was done better AI-Native,
communication cost was very high back then but this I did alone - maybe that's why it worked?
Also strange - looking at domain knowledge, I had written way more proposals, less Skills Consulting.
In terms of tech stack, I used it more heavily back then.
But this time I only used GPTs.
Leadership drive was the same since I drove both.
So nowadays I feel individual components alone
lack explanatory power for why success and failure happen. It's unsatisfying.
But what flashed through my mind was:
"Huh? This is really no different from entrepreneurship" - I reached that thought.
So the core point is, if you think carefully about the first common point between AX and software startups,
success ultimately comes from getting customers to use the new product.
That means customers must overcome
the switching cost from existing to new products.
So Ben Horowitz said
"If you don't make a 10x better product, they won't switch."
That principle.
Zero to One also says 10x.
This concept of 10x utility kept staying in my head.
You need at least that much to overcome switching costs.
It's really similar to startups, I thought.
Ultimately, both startups and AX need to deliver products with 10x utility
to customers,
so you can borrow startup frameworks almost exactly.
In startups, what do we often say when capturing market?
It's crucial to capture a big market.
I'm talking about big markets.
What is "market" in AX?
What is it?
It's time, right?
That time actually means the time spent per organization and workflow type.
That time, that time, that time.
The amounts of time spent are all different markets.
Those times are the market size.
To maintain authority by succeeding with limited resources,
to maintain authority by succeeding with limited resources,
you need to pick where the bottleneck size is large, like with startups.
In startups, we always talk about MVP.
Naturally, we're doing AX through POCs. It seemed like the obvious approach.
It seems like the natural way.
And startups talk a lot about PMF.
In startups, they say you've found PMF when customers pay directly.
So what does finding PMF mean in AX?
It's not just "tried it, liked it" - it needs to be a POC level where they can't go back to the old way to call it finding PMF.
And from a product-market perspective, customers are exactly those organization members using my product.
This means "AI can't find anything."
So whether it's customers I don't know, marketing team, sales team - doesn't matter.
Anyway, I need to match their needs, design user flows so they naturally go through to the end - that's when you've found PMF.
There are investors too. Startups need to prove cash to get VC investment. Who's the investor in AX?
Upper-level decision makers.
When I invest, I...
I need to prove ROI on the resources I extracted for decision makers to invest more in me.
There's runway too. In startups, runway means shutdown when cash runs out.
What's runway and organizational shutdown for an AX team?
Loss of trust.
Right. When internal members' and upper decision makers' trust runs out, it's just shutdown.
Your authority gets taken away.
In terms of difficulty, everyone knows making a startup successful is extremely hard.
I actually view AX as the same difficulty level.
Honestly, if you can succeed at this, you might as well start a company.
At least you'd make more money.
This has no money and it's hard. Painful.
But inevitably it's not quite at that level.
So when I see many people on LinkedIn saying "We did POC, why isn't the next step working?"
Of course. Obviously you made MVP but what comes next is packed like a startup. AX is the same.
What comes after POC is the real deal, so obviously.
POC success doesn't mean
AX success.
From that perspective, if an AX builder is essentially like an entrepreneur, what capability combination is needed to succeed at AX?
So I thought about it, and since today is Echo & Delta meetup,
there's Delta and Echo, but I think additional capabilities are needed beyond that.
What I mean is: PO and PM capabilities must also combine for true AX Full-Stack.
Consultant capabilities mean quickly breaking down problems, structuring bottlenecks, forming hypotheses, iterating logic - but the key is doing it incredibly fast.
Hear it, break it down immediately, run through the logic, run it through agents, "oh the results aren't good," come back and iterate.
Being able to do this really fast means you have AX consultant capabilities.
Obviously PO capabilities are needed too.
What kind of being is a human? How lazy do they hate being?
You need product sense for things people use, concepts of iteration,
and obsession about problem relationships to succeed.
I learned a lot about this at DOIT.
Anyway, PO capabilities with this obsession are needed, and PM too.
Ultimately you need to persuade highly ineffective counterparties while doing AX,
and leadership doesn't give much approval time,
so you need PM capabilities to manage timelines while assembling the plane before hitting the ground,
recovering,
doing POCs, making them successful, doing the main project, etc.
Really no different from an entrepreneur. You'd be better off starting a company.
Anyway.
Still, what mindset should you have when doing AX?
Entrepreneurs think "Nothing is impossible. I've found my thing."
But we need the mindset: "Nothing is impossible for AI. I just prompted it wrong."
Just go at it with everything you've got.
That's my view on the necessary mindset.
So I want to share three playbook items today.
First, going thin but E2E makes it easier to quickly achieve 10X.
Interpreting through the startup framework,
there's always a gap between ideal and reality. As a business unit head who really needs to deliver,
initially you think when you map out the ideal workflow, everyone will follow the textbook organizational workflow,
but absolutely not.
Everyone has their own workflow actually.
So after more detailed interviews, when I charted it,
everyone's proposal-making workflow looks completely different.
Since there's practically no common denominator, attacking a specific bottleneck section of the workflow is actually quite difficult.
So there's the thick and partial approach, or thin but going all the way - I think the right approach is better.
Partially defining some section as a bottleneck and doing AX there is actually targeting only a subset based on some interviewees' bottleneck intersection,
meaning you're likely targeting an even smaller market.
It doesn't become organization-level AX.
With E2E, what can we trust? Not the workflow,
but ultimately any workflow has inputs and outputs.
And everyone uses the same input somehow
to make the final deliverable, the proposal,
the same way.
So approaching E2E has higher likelihood of becoming organization-level AX.
This is the truth.
This is actually not the truth.
Second, going thick and deep handling all edge cases has a very high chance of getting shut down before even doing MVP/POC.
Because they don't give you a month.
Regardless.
"So did you make money? What happened? Why?" - they ask these questions.
So going thin is better,
so the iteration loop can really spin fast and there's higher chance of discovering "that's the real problem."
Actually going thin but E2E was my first painful lesson.
Second, just rebuilding AI-Native from scratch makes achieving 10X somewhat easier.
Elon Musk's first principles thinking is valid for AX too.
Breaking down complex problems to the most basic, fundamental level
is first principles thinking.
"Rockets are expensive so can't be made."
But at that price, what are rockets made of?
Raw materials are these? Not that expensive?
What's the fundamental cost needed for rocket manufacturing?
Like digging into that, when doing AX in organizations and hearing "this requires lots of work, testing alone costs 10 billion,"
rather than just believing that and looking at the workflow,
ultimately we're doing manual labor.
All our activities convert low-value information to high-value information.
All activities.
Since we left manual labor behind in the Industrial Revolution.
So ultimately all acts of creating high-value information -
let's break down all the processes where information value increases.
Then if agents handle this instead of humans, how much testing can be eliminated? Erase everything,
and then automating through AX is much better than starting from human workflows.
Trust only the output and input of work.
Question the taken-for-granted tests in human work when thinking about giving it to agents,
and going AI-Native, simply erasing everything, makes achieving 10X much easier.
That's the second point.
Finally, you must become an AX Full-Stack.
Because before Trust & Patience Burn, before the Runway runs out,
before the trust and patience balance depletes, you need speed to succeed.
So they gave you time, a month passed.
When asked what happened, some effect or transition needs to show
for continued investment from the CEO.
So ultimately you need to be Full-Stack from an AX perspective to succeed at this
in our organization.
In my case, I'm Echo but working hard to become Delta
through Codex and experimenting.
Many of today's attendees are in product roles,
and from that perspective, product-focused engineers and developers
need to keep expanding Delta-to-Echo capability building
to become Full-Stack, gain speed, and succeed.
That's my final conclusion. Thank you.